Guide to the Fellowship of Helen Hadley Hall, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Fellowship of Helen Hadley Hall, Yale University, records
1945-1978
RU 9
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(3 boxes)
The records were created by the chairman of the Fellows of Helen Hadley Hall and include correspondence and memoranda, minutes, reports, directories, photographs of the fellows, notices, and other materials documenting the fellowship and the operation of Helen Hadley Hall. Included are records documenting the visit of Coretta Scott King to the campus in 1969 and Leona Baumgartner as fellow. Also included are records of Frances Blanshard concerning the Committee on the Status and Special Needs of Women at Yale, created by President Charles Seymour in 1945.
Fellowship of Helen Hadley Hall
Yale University. Committee on the Status and Special Needs of Women at Yale
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 25-E (YRG 25-E), Records of departments, offices, programs, and projects of the Graduate School.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from Helen Hadley Hall, 1975. Subsequent gifts from Frances Blanshard, 1977 and 1979, and Claude-Anne Lopez, 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Hadley Hall, a graduate women's residence, was erected on the Yale campus in 1958. In 1961, the Corporation established the Fellowship of Helen Hadley Hall, the first fellowship at Yale open to women. Chairmen of the fellows included Frances B. Blanshard, 1961-1962; Alice Elizabeth Chase, 1962-1970; and Claude-Anne Lopez, 1970-1973. The fellowship was discontinued in 1973, a number of years after women were admitted to residential college fellowships.
Scope and Contents
The records were created by the chairman of the Fellows of Helen Hadley Hall and include correspondence and memoranda, minutes, reports, directories, photographs of the fellows, notices, and other materials documenting the fellowship and the operation of Helen Hadley Hall. Included are records documenting the visit of Coretta Scott King to the campus in 1969 and Leona Baumgartner as fellow. Also included are records of Frances Blanshard concerning the Committee on the Status and Special Needs of Women at Yale, created by President Charles Seymour in 1945.
Coeducation; Women college teachers; Women graduate students -- Scholarships, Fellowships, etc.; Women in education; Women -- Education; Baumgartner, Leona, 1902-1991; Blanshard, Frances Bradshaw, 1895-1966; Chase, Alice Elizabeth; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006; Lopez, Claude-Anne, 1920-2012; Fellowship of Helen Hadley Hall; Yale University -- Funds and scholarships; Yale University -- Student housing; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Frances Blanshard Fellowship Fund; Yale University. Graduate School
- Records, Series I
  - Annual reports, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chairman's book, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chairman's personal files, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Status and Special Needs of Women at Yale, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and subject files
    - General, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
    - Coeducation in Helen Hadley Hall, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Guest suite, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Head resident, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Matters concerning students, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meetings
    - Notices of meetings, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 13)
    - Meeting notes, invitations, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Fellows correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Minutes of meetings, correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Minutes of fellows' meetings, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Reports, announcements of meetings, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Samples of notices, meeting invitations (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Fellows
    - Directories, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - List of fellows, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Membership proposals for fellowships, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Photographs of fellows (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - List of foreign faculty and staff, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Finances, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 27)
  - Frances Blanshard Fellowship Fund
    - Biography of Frances Blanshard, letter, reports, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Drafts of all letters circulated, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Responses from fellows and residents (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Itemized statements of gifts, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Indenture and ledger, Circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Gifts, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Progress reports, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Invitations to candidates, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Proposed fellows, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Fellows
      - Coretta Scott King, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 38 - 39)
      - Leona Baumgartner, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 40 - 42)
  - Opening receptions, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Additonal material from Frances Blanshard (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Additional lists, correspondence, printed materials relating to fellows, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 45)